Guide to the James William Fesler Papers
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
- Additional Material, 1925-1991; Accession 1992-M-081; 1; (1 box)
  - Publications and Papers, 1940-1943
    - 1. "Federal Use of Administrative Areas," Annals of the American Academy of Political and Social Science, 207 (January 1940), pp. 111-115. (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - 2. "Independence of State Regulatory Agencies," American Political Science Review, 34 (October 1940), pp. 935-947. (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - 3. "The Independence of State Utilities Commissions," Journal of Politics, 2 (November 1940), pp. 367-390, and 3 (February 1941), pp. 42-66. (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - 4. "Areas for Industrial Mobilization," Public Administration Review, 1 (Winter 1941), pp. 149-166. (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - 5. ["The Problems of Our Democracy," typescript, addresses to civic forums in Tarboro, N.C., 2/25/41, and Kinston, N.C., 4/2/41--not found] (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - 6. "The North Carolina Local Government Commission," National Municipal Review, 30 (June 1941), pp. 327-334; reprinted in Louisiana Municipal News, 4 (Sept.-Oct. 1941), pp. 149-152. (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - 7. "Relationship of the Office of Production Management to the Defense Program," typescript, Fall 1941. (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - 8. "Relationship of the Supply Priorities and Allocations Board to the Defense Program," typescript, Fall 1941. (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - 9. "Implementation of the Powers of the Supply Priorities and Allocations Board," memorandum to Herbert Emmerich," typescript, December 1941 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - 10. "Southern Political Science Association Program, November 13-15, 1941" [JWF program chairman]. (Not in folder) (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - 11. The Independence of State Regulatory Agencies (Chicago: Public Administration Service, 1942). (Box 1, Folder 5)
      Volume presumably in Yale Library System.
    - 12. "Interdepartmental Relations in the Field Service of the Federal Government," in Donald C. Stone, et al., Washington--Field Relationships in the Federal Service (Washington: Graduate School, U.S. Department of Agriculture, 1942). (Box 1, Folder 5)
      Pamphlet presumably in Government Documents Collection, Yale Library.
    - 13. "Report of the Planning Committee for the Year 1942," January 12, 1943 [drafted by JWF]. (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - 14. "Criteria for Administrative Regions," Social Forces, 22 (October 1943), pp. 26-32. (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Publications and Papers, 1944-1946
    - 1. "The Administrator's Concern in Records Administration," address at Interagency Records Administration Conference, January 28, 1944 (processed). (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - 2. "Discussion Notes of the Committee on Functional Representation, National Planning Association, June 014, 1944--JWF speaker (processed). (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - 3. Ibid., July 5, 1944 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - 4. "The History of the War Production Board: From Monographs to a General History," in "Condensed Minutes, Conference of Historical Officers, Sponsored by Committee on Records of War Administration, Committee on War Studies," December 8, 1944, pp. 20-29 (processed). (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - 5. "Program of the [cancelled] Joint Meeting" of the American Economic Association, American Political Science Association [JWF program chairman], and American Society for Public Administration, February 1-4, 1945 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - 6. "Prepared Statement of J.A. Krug, Chairman of the War Production Board," JWF draft for budget statement to House Appropriations Committee, c. Spring 1945 (typescript). (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - 7. (with associates) War Production in 1944: Report of the Chairman of the War Production Board (Washington: Government Printing Office, June 1945). (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - 8. "Mobilization of Industry for the War," review essay, Public Administration Review 5 (Summer 1945), pp. 257-262. (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - 9. "Abandonment of the Industrial Mobilization Plan," memorandum to J.A. Krug, September 10, 1945, typescript [initial draft by Nathan D. Grundstein]. (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - 10. "Origins of Production Executive Committee," memorandum to J.A. Krug, September 24, 1945, typescript [probably drafted by another]. (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - 11. Letter to the President from J.A. Krug, draft largely followed in Wartime Production Achievements and the Reconversion Outlook: Report of the Chairman, War Production Board, October 9, 1945 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - 12. "Program for War Production Board History," memorandum to G. Lyle Belsley, October 15, 1945 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - 13. "The Historical and Records Program of the War Production Board," in "Historical and Records Program of the War Production Board" (processed, Army Industrial College, December 7, 1945) (Box 1, Folder 6)
      [See also remainder of the document].
    - 14. Minutes of the Planning Committee of the War Production Board (Washington: Government Printing Office, 1946) [JWF, executive secretary]. (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - 15. "Independent Establishments," and "Field Organization," in Fritz Morstein Marx (ed.), Elements of Public Administration (New York: Prentice-Hall, 1946), pp. 207-235, 264-293. (Box 1, Folder 6)
      Volume presumably in Yale University Library system.
    - 16. "Public Administration as a Special Field," in JWF, et al., The University Bureaus of Public Administration (University, Ala.: University of Alabama Press, 1946), pp. 1-10. (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - 17. "Some Problems of Wartime Administration," address to Southern Political Science Association (typescript), November 8, 1946 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Publications and Papers, 1947-1955
    - 1. "Undergraduate Training for the Public Service," American Political Science Review 41 (June 1947), pp. 507-517. (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - 2. (with associates) Industrial Mobilization for War: History of the War Production Board and Predecessor Agencies, 1940-1945: Volume I, Program and Administration (Washington: Government Printing Office, 1947). (Box 1, Folder 7)
      Volume presumably in Government Documents Collection, Yale University Library.
    - 3. "War Production, U.S.," in Ten Eventful Years (Chicago: Encyclopaedia Britannica, 1947), pp. 539-556 and Bibliography, p. 568. [Manuscript also filed] (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - 4. Area and Administration (University, Ala.: University of Alabama Press, 1949). (Box 1, Folder 7)
      Volume in Social Science Library, Yale: JF 1411.F47.1949.
    - 5. Introduction to JWF-edited "Government and Water Resources: A Symposium," American Political Science Review 45 (December 1951), pp. 575-649, at pp. 575-576. (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - 6. "The Problem of the Auxiliary Services," editor's introduction to Centralization of Control and Decentralization of Execution in the Auxiliary Services, a volume of readings for the International Seminar on Problems of General Administration, Brazilian Institute of Public Administration, Getulio Vargas Foundation, 1951 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - 7. "Short Run Movements for Government Reform May Defeat Long Run Objectives," on WTIC "Yale Interprets the News" radio broadcast, November 18, 1951 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - 8. (with others) "Goals for Political Science: A Discussion," American Political Science Review 45 (December 1951), pp. 996-1024 [JWF, pp. 996-1001]. (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - 9. "Administration in the Federal Government," address to Industrial College of the Armed Forces, September 4, 1952 (processed). [Printed in Principles of Administration and Management (Washington: Industrial College of the Armed Forces, 1960]. (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - 10. "One Man's Reasons," address to Greater New Haven Volunteers for Stevenson, September 16, 1952 (processed). (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - 11. Introductory essay to "Treasury vs. Federal Reserve," case study for Government Regulation course (processed). (Box 1, Folder 7)
      Complete case study volume is in Cross Campus Library, Yale: CCL: HG538. F47.
    - 12. ["Republicans Win Sweeping Victory in National Elections," radio talk, November 16, 1952 (Not found)]. (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - 13. Memorandum, "Planning for the American Assembly on Problems of State Government, to be held at Arden House, October 13-15, 1955 (processed). (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - 14. (with associates) The 48 States: Their Tasks as Policy Makers and Administrators (New York: The American Assembly, December 1955). (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Publications and Papers, 1956-1958
    - 1. Las Regiones y la Administracion (translation of Area and Administration ) (San José, Costa Rica: La Escuela Superior de Administration Publica America Central, 1956) (processed). (Box 1, Folder 8)
      Volume in Latin American Collection, Yale University Library.
    - 2. "Budgetary Problems and Field Administration," Memorandum to the [Vietnamese] Committee for the Study of Budgetary and Financial Question[s]," August 3, 1956 (processed). (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - 3. "Some Reflections on Administrative Organization," lecture for government executives of Vietnam, August 16, 1956 (processed). (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - 4. "Field Administration in Vietnam: A Memorandum for the President [Ngo Dinh Diem], August 21, 1956 (processed). (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - 5. "Report on Vietnam," WTIC radio broadcast of "Yale Reports," December 2, 1956 (processed). (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - 6. "Administrative Literature and the Second Hoover Commission Reports," American Political Science Review 51 (March 1957), pp. 135-157. (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - 7. "National Water Resources Administration," Law and Contemporary Problems 22 (Summer 1957), pp. 444-471. (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - 8. "Administration in the Federal Government," Lecture to Industrial College of the Armed Forces, August 30, 1957 (processed, Industrial College). (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - 9. "Public Service--At Home," "Public Service--Abroad," "Politics," for Yale Placement Service's pamphlet on career opportunities (typescripts, August 1957). (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - 10. "Some Reflections on Administrative Organization," processed English version of article in Vietnamese language, Administrative Research, I, No. 1 (September 1957), pp. 56-72. (Box 1, Folder 8)
      Vietnamese journal in Southeast Asia Collection, Yale University Library.
    - 11. "Appropriation," "Commission," "Public Administration," articles for UNESCO Social Science Dictionary (typescripts, November 1957). (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - 12. "Yale's Role in the Study and Practice of Government," Remarks to the Yale and Government Committee of the Yale Club of Washington, February 25, 1958 (processed). (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - 13. "Remarks at Caucus Room, Senate Office Building--Yale Club of Washington reception honoring Yale men in Congress, February 25, 1958 (typescript). (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - 14. "The Role of the Review " and "Specialist and Generalist," editorials in Public Administration Review 18 (Summer 1958), p. 271, and (Autumn 1958), p. 370. (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - 15. "The Capacity to Govern," dinner address, Vermont Assembly on State Government, Montpelier, September 26, 1958 (processed). [Published in Rolf N. B. Haugen and E. William Steele (eds.), Vermont--The 14th Original State (Government Clearing House, University of Vermont, 1959)], pp. 102-110. (Box 1, Folder 8)
      Volume presumably in Yale Library system.
    - 16. "Authority," "Hoover Commission," "Region," articles for World Book Encyclopedia (typescripts, November 1958). (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Publications and Papers, 1980-1984
    - 1. "Foreword" to Donald F. Kettl, Managing Community Development in the New Federalism (New York: Praeger, 1980). Typescript [published version rife with errata]. (Box 1, Folder 13)
      Volume in Sterling Memorial Library: HN79. C83. C64.
    - 2. Public Administration: Theory and Practice (Englewood Cliffs, N.J.: Prentice-Hall, 1980). (Box 1, Folder 13)
      Volume in Social Science Library: JF1351. F47
    - 3. "A Social Science 'Fraternity' in Washington and Academe," News for Teachers of Political Science (Winter 1981), pp. 26-27 (excerpt from Oral History). (Box 1, Folder 13)
    - 4. "The Editors Interview James W. Fesler," New England Journal of Human Services 2 (Fall 1982), pp. 6-12. (Box 1, Folder 13)
      Presumably in Yale Library System.
    - 5. JWF (ed.), American Public Administration: Patterns of the Past (Washington: American Society for Public Administration, 1982). (Box 1, Folder 13)
      —"The Presence of the Administrative Past," introduction at pp. 1-27. Volume in Social Science Library: JF1351. A585.
    - 6. "The Institutional Presidency and Policy Formation," remarks at Center for the Presidency's 13th Annual Leadership Conference, November 6, 1982 (typescript). (Box 1, Folder 13)
    - 7. "Politics, Policy, and Bureaucracy at the Top," Annals of the American Academy of Political and Social Science 466 (April 1983), pp. 23-41. (Box 1, Folder 13)
    - 8. "The Higher Civil Service in Europe and the United States," in Bruce L. R. Smith (ed.), The Higher Civil Service in Europe and Canada: Lessons for the United States (Washington: The Brookings Institution, 1984), pp. 87-92. (Box 1, Folder 13)
      Volume in Social Science Library: JN94. A69. E935.
    - 9. Remarks at Bob Lane's retirement (typescript, 1984). (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Publications and Papers, 1959-1960
    - 1. "Asphalt vs. Concrete, and Other Comparisons," editorial, Public Administration Review 19 (Winter 1959), p. 70. (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - 2. "Statement in support of House Bill 2848 [for a referendum on calling a constitutional convention] before Committee on the Judiciary and Governmental Functions, Connecticut General Assembly, April 9, 1959 (typescript carbon). (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - 3. "Administrative Areas," Encyclopedia Britannica (1959 et seq.), vol. I, pp. 150-151. (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - 4. "The Role of America's Loyal Opposition" (with Adlai Stevenson and William Miller), WTIC "Yale Reports" radio broadcast, May 3, 1959 (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - 5. "Reflections on Administrative Organization," paper prepared for session on Pathologies of Administration, Brookings Institution Conference, Williamsburg, Virginia, May 1959 (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - 6. "Presentation of the Portrait of Thomas C. Mendenhall to Berkeley College," June 7, 1959 (typescript carbon). (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - 7. "Creative Decade for Administration," editorial, Public Administration Review 19 (Spring 1959), p. 144. (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - 8. "Connecticut's Body Politic," address to Connecticut League of Women Voters, June 9, 1959 (typescript carbon). (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - 9. "Across Time and Space," editorial, Public Administration Review 19 (Summer 1959), p. 215. (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - 10. "Programming Research--Linear or Circular," editorial, Public Administration Review 19 (Summer 1959), p. 285. (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - 11. "Independent Regulatory Agencies" and "Field Organization," in Fritz Morstein Marx (ed.), Elements of Public Administration (2nd edition, New York: Prentice-Hall, 1959), pp. 191-218, 246-273. (Box 1, Folder 9)
      Volume in Yale Cross Campus Library: JF 1351.M67.1959.
    - 12. "Patterns of Field Administration," paper for Eastern Administrators Conference, American Society for Public Administration, December 3, 1959 (processed). (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - 13. "In Analyzing University Administration," editorial, Public Administration Review 20 (Winter 1960), p. 59. (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - 14. "The Politics of 1960," dinner address to the Connecticut Life Insurance and Trust Council and the Junior Bar Section of the State Bar Association, March 30, 1960. (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - 15. "Leadership and Its Context," editorial, Public Administration Review 20 (Spring 1960), p. 122. (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - 16. "The Use of Government Publications in Research and Teaching in American Government," for political science graduate students (processed, 1960). (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - 17. "The Role of the Citizen in Politics: The Function of the Presidency" (with Robert. A. Dahl and H. Bradford Westerfield), WTIC "Yale Reports" radio broadcast, November 6, 1960 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Publications and Papers, 1961-1963
    - 1. "Comparative Perspectives on the Areal Organization of Administration," paper for annual meeting, American Political Science Association, September 8, 1961 (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - 2. "Patterns of Decentralization in the United States of America," paper for the United Nations Working Group on Administrative Aspects of Decentralization for Development, Geneva, October 16-27, 1961. [for printed version, see item 7 below]. (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - 3. (JWF, rapporteur) "Draft Report: Size of Areas and Number of Tiers for Field Administration and Local Government," at UN Group meeting, Geneva, October 23, 1961. (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - 4. "The Case Method in Political Science," in Edwin A. Bock (ed.), Essays on the Case Method in Public Administration (Brussels: International Institute of Administrative Sciences, 1962), pp. 65-88. (Box 1, Folder 10)
      Volume in Social Science Library, Yale: JF 1351.I58 [Author: Inter-University Case Program].
    - 5. "The Political Role of Field Administration," in Ferrel Heady and Sybil L. Stokes (eds.), Papers in Comparative Public Administration (Ann Arbor: Institute of Public Administration, University of Michigan, 1962). (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - 6. "French Field Administration: The Beginnings," Comparative Studies in Society and History 5 (October 1962), pp. 71-111. (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - 7. "Patterns of Decentralization in the United States of America," Annex III J in United Nationals Technical Assistance Programme (Division for Public Administration, Department of Economic and Social Affairs, Decentralization for National and Local Development (New York: United Nations, 1962), pp. 207-215. (Box 1, Folder 10)
      Volume presumably in Government Documents Collection, Yale Library System.
    - 8. "Administration in the Federal Government," in Fred R. Brown (ed.), Management: Concepts and Practice (Washington: Industrial College of the Armed Force, 1963), pp. 121-138. (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - 9. "Needed: A Field Management Typology," in Alan L. Dean (ed.), Federal Agency Approaches to Field Management (Chicago: American Society for Public Administration, 1963), pp. 24-25. (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - 10. Remarks (with those of others) at Memorial Service for Francis W. Coker, May 23, 1963 (processed). (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - 11. "Foreword" to Herbert Jacob, German Administration Since Bismarck (New Haven: Yale University Press, 1963). (Box 1, Folder 10)
      Volume in Cross Campus Library: JN 3548. J33. 1963.
    - 12. "Foreword" to Robert C. Fried, The Italian Prefects (New Haven: Yale University Press, 1963). (Box 1, Folder 10)
      Volume in Cross Campus Library: JS5738. F75.
  - Publications and Papers, 1964-1969
    - 1. "Approaches to the Understanding of Decentralization," paper presented at the 6th World Congress of the International Political Science Association, Geneva, September 21-25, 1964 (Box 1, Folder 11)
    - 2. "Regional and Local Organisation of Central Governments: A General View," public lecture, London School of Economics and Political Science, November 3, 1964 (typescript). (Box 1, Folder 11)
    - 3. "National Water Resources Administration," in Stephen K. Smith and Emery N. Castle (eds.), Economics and Public Policy in Water Resources Development (Ames, Iowa: Iowa State University Press, 1964), pp. 368-402 (updated revision of 1957 article of same title). (Box 1, Folder 11)
      Volume in Cross Campus Library: HD1694.A5.S65.
    - 4. "Considerazioni sul Significato del Decentramento," Rivista Internationale di Scienze Socialis [Milan] 73 (1965), fasc. II, pp. 140-163. (Box 1, Folder 11)
    - 5. "Approaches to the Understanding of Decentralization," Journal of Politics 27 (August 1965), pp. 536-566. (Box 1, Folder 11)
    - 6. "Remarks for the Committee on the Leonard D. White Memorial Award," American Political Science Association annual meeting, September 8, 1966 (Box 1, Folder 11)
    - 7. JWF (ed.), The 50 States and Their Local Governments (New York: Alfred A. Knopf, 1967). (Box 1, Folder 11)
      Volume in Cross Campus Library: JK408. F47. 1967.
    - 8. "Departmental and Interdepartmental Field Administration," paper prepared for the President's [Heineman] Task Force on Government Organization, Mar1967 (Box 1, Folder 11)
    - 9. "The Federal Bureaucracy," lecture at the Air War College, Maxwell Air Force Base, Alabama, October 12, 1967 (Box 1, Folder 11)
    - 10. "Cutting the Suit to Fit the Cloth," talk before the Yale Club of New Haven, November 6, 1967 (Box 1, Folder 11)
    - 11. "El problema de la descentralization sus enfoques interpretatives," Revista de Administración Publica [Buenos Aires] VII, No. 26-27 (Julio-Decembre 1967), pp. 42-74. (Box 1, Folder 11)
      Issue presumably in Latin American Collection, Yale Library.
    - 12. Letter to James E. Webb, Administrator, National Aeronautics and Space Administration, April 25, 1968 (typescript). (Box 1, Folder 11)
    - 13. "Centralization and Decentralization," Encyclopedia of the Social Sciences (1968), vol. 2, pp. 370-379. (Box 1, Folder 11)
    - 14. "Federalism," remarks at National Academy of Public Administration, December 6, 1968 (Box 1, Folder 11)
    - 15. Letter to Sen. Lee Metcalf, February 26, 1969, in Utility Consumers' Counsel Act of 1969: Hearings before Subcommittee on Intergovernmental Relations of Senate Committee on Government Operations (Washington: GPO, 1969), pp. 233-234. (Box 1, Folder 11)
    - 16. Remarks at Yale Department dinner for Herbert and Ruth Kaufman, May 30, 1969 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Publications and Papers, 1970-1977
    - 1. "T-Group Movement," letter to the editor, Public Administration Review 30 (September/October 1970), pp. 580-582. (Box 1, Folder 12)
    - 2. "The Basic Theoretical Question: How to Relate Area and Function," in Leigh E. Grosenick (ed.), The Administration of the New Federalism (Washington: American Society for Public Administration, 1973), pp. 4-14. (Box 1, Folder 12)
      Volume in Cross Campus & Social Science Libraries: JK 325.TA525.
    - 3. Remarks in "A Mini-Symposium: President Nixon's Proposals for Executive Reorganization," Public Administration Review 34 (September/October 1974), pp. 490-491. (Box 1, Folder 12)
    - 4. "Public Administration and the Social Sciences: 1946-1960," in Frederick C. Mosher (ed.), American Public Administration: Past, Present, Future (University, Ala.: University of Alabama Press, 1975), pp. 97-141. (Box 1, Folder 12)
      Volume in Cross Campus Library: JF.1338. A2. A67.
    - 5. [with 3 other members] Committee on the Structure of [Connecticut] State Government, Better Organization for Better Government: Report (1976). (Box 1, Folder 12)
    - 6. "Testimony before the Committee on Government Administration and Policy of the Connecticut General Assembly, April 4, 1977 (typescript). (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Publication and Papers, 1987-1991
    - 1. "in re Robert A. Dahl," remarks at retirement, March 19, 1987 (typescript). (Box 1, Folder 14)
    - 2. "The Brownlow Committee Fifty Years Later," Public Administration Review 47 (July/August 1987), pp. 291-296. (Box 1, Folder 14)
      —Also in Frederick C. Mosher (ed.), The President Needs Help (Lanham, Md.: University Press of America, 1988), pp. 8-22, 41-46. (Volume presumably in Yale Library System.)
    - 3. "Reflections of a Civil Servant," The Bureaucrat 16 (Summer 1987), pp. 3-5. (Box 1, Folder 14)
    - 4. "The Higher Public Service in Western Europe," in Ralph Clark Chandler (ed.), A Centennial History of the American Administrative State (New York: Free Press, 1987), pp. 509-539. (Box 1, Folder 14)
      Volume in Social Science Library: JK411. C46. 1987.